A Guide to Kathryn H. Stone, Papers concerning Reston, Va. 1959-1983
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Kathryn H. Stone, Papers concerning Reston, Va. 1959-1983
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10555
ca. 1600 items (18 Hollinger boxes, two scrapbooks, and an oversize folder, ca. 6.5 linear feet)
This collection consists of correspondence, memoranda, notes, plans, reports, newspapers and other printed material, and photographs, 1959-1983, pertaining to the development and management of the new town, Reston, Virginia and other new towns in the United States and elsewhere, compiled by Kathryn H. Stone.
Kathryn H. Stone
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated to the Library by Kathryn H. Stone, July 12, 1983.
Biographical/Historical Information
Kathryn H. Stone was the director of the Program on Human Resources and of the Reston Study from 1963 to 1968. In 1969, she was the executive vice chairman of the Commission on Human Resources, a constituent agency of the Washington Center for Metropolitan Studies (WCMS), and also senior associate of WCMS. Robert E. Simon, Jr., conceived the idea of Reston, and planning and financing were his specialties during its development.
Michael Vincent DiSalle, the ex-governor of Ohio, was hired by Simon as president and chief executive officer of the Reston operation in the spring of 1963, where he remained until his resignation some eight months later. DiSalle was given responsibility for administration and execution within the project.
Carol Lubin operated both in Reston and New York, thus being somewhat of a liaison officer with Simon (whose family corporations were based in New York) in addition to her formally allotted duties in the field of planning for Reston's community activities and community relations. She handled relations with churches, the school board, county libraries, parks, recreation areas, and health departments. She was one of Simon's first appointments and took part in early discussions of Reston's social proposals.
Scope and Content Information
These papers were compiled by Stone for Reston, Virginia ... A Study in Beginnings, prepared for the Washington Center for Metropolitan Studies. They include correspondence, memoranda, plans, reports, maps, articles, photographs, and Stone's summaries regarding the early development and management of Reston by Robert E. Simon, and its takeover by Gulf Reston Corporation.
Persons involved with Reston and/or the Washington Center for Metropolitan Studies history of Reston include the donor, Kathryn H. Stone; the founder of Reston, Robert E. Simon, Jr.; Michael Vincent DiSalle; and Carol Lubin. Much of the material pertains to their activities on behalf of Reston.
The papers contain minutes, legal and financial material for the Homeowner's Associations; speeches by Simon; Stone's correspondence regarding Reston and the study; printed material pertaining to Reston, Greater Washington, Gulf Reston, and new towns in general; issues of the Reston Times, 1963-1975; scrap books; photographs of Reston, and drafts of Stone's study.
Topics include low income housing, administration and administrative conflicts, community relations and community development programs, industrial development, early planning by Harland Bartholomew and Whittlesley and Conklin, transportation, sales, educational programs and facilities, and financing.
Organization
The collection is divided into five series: Office Files; Printed Material; Bound Volumes; Photographs; and Oversize Material. The folders are arranged alphabetically within each series. Original folder headings have been retained with some modifications.
Contents List
- Office Files 1959-1972 (Box 1-9)
  - Administration: Cluster Associations--By-Laws, Guides, etc. 1967, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Administration: Correspondence 1961-1968, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Administration: Covenants and By-Laws 1963-1966 (Box 1)
  - Administration: Interviews with WCMS Staff 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Administration: Legal Files 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Administration: Lubin Memos and Statements 1962-1964, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Adminstration: Sales Evaluation 1963 (Box 1)
  - Administration: Service Branch Information 1966 (Box 1)
  - "The Beginnings: from the Bowman brothers to Robert E. Simon, Jr.: 1927-1961" n.d., 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Community Relations: Ad Hoc Committee to keep Reston "Reston" 1968 (Box 1)
  - Community Relations: Community Association--Minutes, Releases, etc. 1966-1969 (Box 1)
  - Community Relations: Gulf-Reston STudy of the Homeowners Associations in Reston 1969 (Box 1)
  - Community Relations: Home Owners Association 1964-1970, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Community Relations: Home Owners Association Study 1972 (Box 2)
  - Community Relations: Reston "Flyer" 1964-1967 (Box 2)
  - Community Relations: Statistical Surveys 1966-1968, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Disalle, Michael V. 1963 (Box 2)
  - Education: Elementary 1965-1967 (Box 2)
  - Education: Fairfax County System 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Education: Special--Music 1969 (Box 2)
  - Education: University of Virginia Newsletter 1966-1968 (Box 2)
  - Federal Government: Laws and Handbooks 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Financing 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - Financing: Economy Seminar 1964 (Box 2)
  - Financial: Hercer Corporation 1963 (Box 2)
  - Foundation Administration: Board Meetings, Members, and Reports 1966-1969 (Box 2)
  - Foundation Administration: Grant Proposal 1966-1968, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Foundation Administration: Health Care 1963-1968, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Foundation Administration: HUD Grant 1961-1969 (Box 3)
  - Foundation Administration: HUD Grant Related Studies 1966-1969 (Box 3)
  - Foundation Administration: Nature Center 1965-1967 (Box 3)
  - Foundation Administration: Organization Charts 1967-1968, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Foundation Administration: Proposals, Miscellaneous 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - Grant Proposals: Other Sources 1966 (Box 3)
  - Grant Proposals: WCMS 1963, 1966-1967, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Housing in Fairfax County 1963-1964 (Box 3)
  - Housing in Fairfax County: "Housing Preferences of Persons Employed in Reston, Virginia" 1968 (Box 3)
  - Industrial Development: Brochures--General 1961-1969, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Industrial Development: Industrial Center for Research and Development 1964-1965, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Maps: Reston--Overall & Neighborhood 1962-1966, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Metro Fair Housing: Proposals 1964-1968 (Box 4)
  - Metro Fair Housing: Race Studies--General 1963, 1969 (Box 4)
  - New Towns: Asia, Britain, Europe 1964-1969 (Box 4)
  - New Towns: Bibliographies 1965-1969 1960-1967, n.d. (Box 4)
  - New Towns: Bibliographies--Ministry of Housing Survey 1959, 1962 (Box 4)
  - New Towns: Columbia 1964-1970, n.d. (Box 4)
  - New Towns: Columbia--Handbook for Residents 1970 (Box 4)
  - New Towns: Correspondence & Memos 1963-1970 (Box 4)
  - New Towns: Europe 1964-1969 (Box 5)
  - New Towns: Fort Lincoln 1964-1969, n.d. (Box 5)
  - New Towns: Governmental Problems 1965 (Box 5)
  - New Towns: Metropolitan D.C. 1964-1965 (Box 5)
  - New towns: Miscellaneous Plans 1962-1968 (Box 5)
  - New Towns: Problems 1962-1966, n.d. (Box 5)
  - New Towns: U.S.A. 1962-1971, n.d. (Box 5)
  - New Towns: WCMS Studies 1962-1966, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Planning: Bartholomew Plan 1961-1964 (Box 5)
  - Planning: Armistead Boothe 1961-1962 (Box 5)
  - Planning: Church Planning 1962, 1966, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Planning: Fairfax County Reston Proposal and Approval ca. 1960 (Box 6)
  - Planning: Fairfax County Reston--Zoning 1961-1968 (Box 6)
  - Planning: Arthur D. Little, Inc. 1962 (Box 6)
  - Planning: Miscellaneous 1961-1964 (Box 6)
  - Planning: Preliminary Master Plan for Reston 1961-1965, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Planning: Regional--General 1964-1965 (Box 6)
  - Planning: Regional--re Reston 1961-1965 (Box 6)
  - Planning: Residential Planned Community Zoning 1963-1972, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Planning: Whittlesley and Conklin 1962-1964 (Box 6)
  - Recreation: Sports 1968, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Research: Attidudinal Surveys 1965-1967 (Box 7)
  - Research: Bibliographies 1964-1971 (Box 7)
  - Research: Evaluations of Reston n.d. (Box 7)
  - Research: GWRC's "Financial Projections for Major Local Goverments in the Washington Area, 1982-1987" by Philip M. Dearborn 1982, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Research: Local Government and New Town (J.R. Seiger) 1967-1968 (Box 7)
  - Research: Miscellaneous Studies re Reston 1962-1964, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Research: Notes on "Reston in the Doldrums: 1963" 1964 (Box 7)
  - Research: Reston Notebook n.d. (Box 7)
  - Reaearch: Transportation System--WCMS Study 1968-1969 (Box 7)
  - Research: WCMS Studies Miscellaneous 1960-1962 (Box 8)
  - Research: WCMS Studies Miscellaneous 1963-1967 (Box 8)
  - Research: WCMS Studies Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 8)
  - Reston: List of Materials for Reston Study n.d. (Box 8)
  - Reston, Virginia...A Study in Beginnings, Chapters 1-11 1966, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - "Reston, Virginia: Vision of a New Town"--Readings compiled and edited by Kathryn H. Stone and Fred Flaxman ca. 1970, 1 of 2 folders (Box 8)
  - "Reston, Virginia: Vision of a New Town"--Readings compiled and edited by Kathryn H. Stone and Fred Flaxman ca. 1970, 10 of 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Simon: Speeches 1963-1967 (Box 9)
  - Stone: Correspondence 1963, 1966-1967 (Box 9)
  - Stone: Correspondence 1968-1969 (Box 9)
  - Stone: Memoranda 1964-1967, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Stone: Notes re Reston 1964-1969, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Stone: Miscellaneous Articles 1959-1969, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute: Inviational New Communities Symposium, August 17-21, 1970 1961-1970, n.d. (Box 9)
  - The Washington Center for Metropolitan Studies--Memoranda 1962-1965 (Box 9)
  - The Washington Center for Metropolitan Studies--Records 1961-1965 (Box 9)
- Printed Material 1959-1983 (Box 10-17)
  - Printed material re Fairfax County 1962-1968 (Box 10)
  - Printed material re Greater Washington Region 1959-1982, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Printed material re Gulf-Reston Corporation 1967 (Box 10)
  - Printed material re New Towns 1960-1966, n.d. (Box 10)
  - Printed material re New Towns: Plannings 1963-1972 (Box 10)
  - Printed material re Reston 1962-1964 (Box 10)
  - Printed material re Reston 1965-1083, n.d., 4 folders (Box 11)
  - The Reston Times 1965-1969, 7 folders (Box 12)
  - The Reston Times 1970 Jan-Oct, 5 folders (Box 13)
  - The Reston Times 1970 Nov-1971 Jun, 4 folders (Box 14)
  - The Reston Times 1972 Jan-Aug, 7 folders (Box 16)
  - The Reston Times 1972-Sep-1973 Mar, 5 folders (Box 17)
- Reston Low Income Housing Demonstration Program 1969, bound volume (Box 18)
- Reston, Virginia...A Study in Beginnings(Volume I) 1969, bound volume (Box 18)
- Reston, Virginia...A Study in Beginnings(Volume II-Appendix) 1966, bound volume (Box 18)
- Photographs and art work re Reston n.d.
- Scrapbook of clippings re "Reston...A New Town in the United States" [1964], bound volume
- Scrapbook of photographs re "Reston, Virginia...Its Beginnings" [1966], bound volume
- Photographs and art work re Reston n.d. (Box E-5)